Guide to the Ballard's Valley and Berry Hill Penn Plantation Records, 1766-1873
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ballard's Valley and Berry Hill Penn Plantation records 1766-1873
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ballard's Valley Plantation (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica)
6.0 linear feet Extent: 244 Items
Plantations in St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica. Records of sugar and livestock plantations in St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica. The material prior to 1837 is chiefly plantation records. Later papers include letters from managers of the estate to the owners describing crop conditions, trouble with freed blacks in 1838, the importation of coolies in 1846, sugar traders' reaction to the repeal of the corn laws in that year, and plans for the erection of a Church of England chapel in 1848. The plantation records reveal the number and condition of slaves and stock, purchases of goods, accounts payable, size of crops, and sales of sugar, rum, and cattle.
ballardsvalley
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ballard's Valley and Berry Hill Penn Plantation Records were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1957.
Collection Overview
This series contains 235 items and 9 volumes of the records of sugar and livestock plantations, Ballard's Valley Plantation and Berry Hill Penn, in St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica. The material prior to 1837 is chiefly plantation records, including financial papers and account books. The plantation records reveal the number and condition of slaves or apprentices and stock, purchases of goods, accounts payable, size of crops, and sales of sugar, rum, and cattle. Later papers include letters from managers of the estate to the owners describing crop conditions, trouble with freed Negroes in 1838, the importation of Chinese laborers in 1846, sugar traders' reaction to the repeal of the corn laws in that year, and plans for the erection of a Church of England chapel in 1848.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Church of England -- Jamaica; Plantations -- Jamaica; Slavery -- Jamaica; Sugar trade -- Jamaica; Livestock -- Breeding -- Jamaica; Corn laws (Great Britain); Immigrants -- Chinese -- Jamaica; Jamaica -- History; Ballard's Valley Plantation (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica); Berry Hill Penn (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica)
Contents of Collection
- Papers, 1766-1848, (4 boxes)
  - Papers, 1766-1827 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1828-1839 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1840-1848 and undated (Box 3)
  - Volumes (Box 3)
  - Photocopies (Box 4)
- Bound Volumes, 1773-1848, (8 volumes)
  - Account book, 1793-1804 (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume ff:5660)
  - Account book, 1793-1809 (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume ff:5661)
  - Account book, 1831-1839 St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume F:5662)
  - Ledger, 1793-1806 (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume F:5663)
  - Ledger, 1838-1846 (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume F:5664)
  - Ledger, 1847-1848 (St. Mary's Parish, Jamaica) (Volume F:5665)
  - Cruickshank, John and James: Ledger, 1773-1825 (London, England) (Volume F:5666)
  - Cruickshank, John and James: Ledger, 1793-1806 (London, England) (Volume F:5667)
- Oversize Materials, (3 folders)
  - Supply lists, accounts, etc., 1807-1848 (Opaperfolder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous (Opaperfolder 3)